this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
[Music]
okay welcome listeners to another
episode of software engineering radio
this one is recorded at the Europe lope
2009 not that that's important but I
thought I mention it
in this episode we are going to talk
about management about how to become a
manager why and what you have to do to
be a good manager of course all of this
in the context of software engineering
or software development
so in some sense this is a successor or
a detailed episode to the roles episodes
we've had a while ago and well I guess
over time we will present more topics
maybe at some point we'll get around to
do something on you know what does it
take to be a consultant because that's
one of these other roles we've had but
today we are going to talk about
management and well you probably
recognize that it's me Marcos talking
and asking the questions and on the
other end is Amir
hi Marcos well we've done several
episodes before on various technical
topics so people might ask themselves
why am i interviewing you about being or
becoming or managing so so maybe you
want to say something about what's
changed in your professional life and
then we can yeah the change in my
professional life happened two years ago
when I changed into a management
position from previously consultant and
technical lead and expert position and
so basically what what we're talking
about is my experience over the past I
would say more than 10 years but more
concretely the past two years and some
recommendations findings that I
experienced and I thought it would be
worthwhile to do an episode on and well
as the disclaimer is really my private
and personal opinion of course some
somewhat synchronized with typical HR
strategies but still it's it's a
personal opinion and considered yourself
what you make out of it ok so so maybe
let's start by
you know defining what management is and
what makes a good manager I think a good
manager is one that that cares about
people very much and in the first place
and it's about results it's about
leading the people towards achieving
good to create results it's not so much
about deciding everyday by your own it's
much more stimulating the organization
the teams below you your team members to
act proactively to do their to do a good
job every day and become better every
day on it and support them and and then
sometimes the situations will arise
where you actually have to make a
decision where you have to make a
informed and hopefully context-sensitive
decision are these than technical
decisions or are these typically more
decisions regarding organization or
staffing so that those people you want
to be in charge then make the right
technical decisions right
so it's it's mostly about strategy it's
about organization it's about people
those decisions that you would do as a
R&D manager it's less about any
technical choices if it's really it's if
it's a true cornerstone in your strategy
which determines your business in the
course of the next five or ten years the
R&D manager typically is involved and
gets the presentation from the relevant
staff like for example the architect
together with the product manager they
prepare decision proposal and it's
basically reviewed by a by one R&D
manager or actually a committee where
you look at it and read check whether it
is sound whether they covered all the
aspect and whether it's a holistic view
on the topic whether it's not only bias
by one
by Bourne angle of it so you've
mentioned that your job as a manager is
among hello things to lead people and to
motivate people to do good work where do
you lead them to how do you how do you
know where you want to go as a manager
once you go who set your goals the goals
is basically in a large company it's
it's my organization it's it's my
mission I actually had thought of saving
this discussion about mission vision and
strategy but why don't I bore you
briefly right now with it yeah you
really you really got involved very
deeply into this management stuff since
you're trying to find the difference
between those three terms so so let's
try I think it's I think it's important
to be honest in the past or very early
in my career I mix them up and I was not
sure whether this is actually necessary
because well all the problems we're at
hand
looking at the daily work but really
looking only at the daily work that's
not sufficient I mean you know need to
look one or several years actually ahead
where you want to be and there we come
to the mission I mean who are you who
are you as an organization why are you
making a difference to the world to your
customers
why should customers actually buy
something from you so who who are you is
the mission so in the typical mission
would be we strive for good customer
relations well this would be bit too
generic valve and we sorta cost provoke
yeah we are for example we are the best
in image visualization and this on that
domain okay this is really our our core
competence so it's it's a way of
identifying your core competency also
right and giving an expression to it
right okay so what you're really good
about it
were you organization you're people get
excited about it I mean this is I so
often in life what you can get excited
about it you will most probably be good
in
and were you good and you will have
success and all the business success
ultimately then this was the mission
thing so you know who you are
next is the division I mean where should
you strive for for for example within
the next five years or so right like
drawing a goal which is ahead of you I
mean an ambitious goal really becoming
the market leader in this and this and
that market with this and that kind of
product ok would be for example a vision
and then that is the goal and now what's
missing that's the path how to reach
that goal that's the strategy ultimately
so how can I reach how do I blend to
reach that goal the ultimate goal so
going back to my original question
although I think this is an interesting
discussion because many software people
laugh about these terms right vision
vision strategy blah you know management
buzzword right exactly they also need
their passwords right not just the
technical people but so how does this
tie into the question of that I asked
before well you know how do you know
where you need to go what you need to
motivate you people to get to I mean
that is then what you as a manager at
any level derive from your
organization's mission and vision this
is your strategy and you can really
translate your strategy into operative
goals
for the next half year for the next year
where you really decide on how to
approach to reach the goals and it helps
you all progress or to prioritize things
you need to do because if they don't get
you you know ahead on your strategy
towards your vision then probably you
shouldn't do them right so this is
really than the healthy filter applied
to all activities that you do check for
skin through your activities today
support your strategy or don't day and
if as I would guess in in most
organizations today you are overloaded
by stuff yes look at things that really
don't support your strategy and either
you
strategy is wrong or you're doing
actually superfluous stuff or things
that don't don't lead you to your to
your goal so if you're some kind of
manager of a 10 team ten people
development team very deep down in the
corporate hierarchy I guess it's not
very useful to take the company mission
vision strategy to derive from so in
some sense isn't is it the case that
like every department needs its vision
and you know do these terms apply
hierarchically down the you know chart
basically you make it more concrete at
every level you express there your more
details give it more details and make it
more concrete in your environment but
you coordinate yourself with your
superior manager whether that is in line
with his understanding of the division
and the strategy so you're basically
saying you understand the vision mission
and strategy of your of the organization
above you where you are you know the set
of your peers and the boss of the world
the well your boss basically the mission
vision strategy of your boss's
organization right and then you come up
with your own one and then recheck that
with with with your boss whether he
agrees and that's the guidance for where
and how you lead that's the guidance for
example for the next year how you lead
and of course you try to line out how
would that work over the next two or
three years horizon and it's that
concrete enough I mean I guess the
strategy is maybe two pages the vision
is one sentence the mission is two
sentences I mean what other input do you
get from your boss on a daily basis I
mean how how does that work well the
daily input you would get basically is
conversations with the customers where
you learn well where is the market going
where our customers going what is really
going on around me in the organization
this has of course impact on what I'm
doing daily how I'm leading it it forms
the initiatives and the strategy is as I
said
maura filter to find the right
initiatives finding the right actions to
do in your in your daily work
so as you said you've you've changed
your career from a very technical path
to this management kind of thing and do
you think and of course you're still
managing in a software environment you
know well software's and everything but
software is a big part of what your
company is building so is it essential
that you have developed software before
how important is the detailed technical
understanding for what you're doing
well there I I have partly I had heavy
discussions with with peers and
superiors where some say well at a
certain level you need to be a general
manager more than really an technical
expert or anything or maybe it gets you
into the way and actually you have to be
careful not to tell people the solution
but challenge them on the problem
understanding so that they find a
solution so when you don't get into your
way with your or when the technical
knowledge and understanding doesn't get
into your way but supports you then it's
a very good idea to have have been a
software developer and with getting in
your way you mean that you don't try to
make that the technical decisions for
your experts right because nothing is
more boring and frustrating for every
employee for every developer architect
whatever then when the boss tells you
exactly do this and that
I mean we're we all knowledge workers we
work with our brains we are motivated by
the freedom and empowerment we get and
by telling your employees what they
should do exactly as the next five steps
today tomorrow and the day after that
that's very frustrating and that's
that's a big caveat that you can fall
into so you use your technical expertise
to look behind the passwords to you know
to avoid bingo and to ask the
right question in order to lead the
others to the right right was to to
challenge to find actually the best
solutions not proposing the solutions
but
being really being able to do
context-sensitive decisions and and
supporting my guys because well I
believe only if you truly understand
what kind of problems they face what how
difficult it could be to solve any
specific kind of bugs that you have then
you can support them best I mean you
don't have well solve it till tomorrow
but when you see well they have doesn't
that stability trouble you need you know
that it takes time and you also know
what it needs to take on an action so
you can support your team if they are
not support so experience that and give
them some guidance and hints what they
could try and look at and look into if
you haven't been in such a position well
the team might fail you get pretty
frustrated with you can always hire some
other guys some kind of quote consultant
who brings in that knowledge so you
could argue that as a manager you don't
have to know these things you have to
know when the time is right to get
external help I'm not saying that's
right just provoking of course so that's
that's right I mean you don't need to
understand exactly but you need to have
a gut feeling and a gut feeling at a
what is that ten thousand feet level
this this this right is this wrong does
this lead us in the right direction and
for any detailed guidance you would
actually hire a consultant or get an
expert from a neighbor yeah
neighbor Department so don't you miss
the technical work I mean you've you've
done all this thing to the work you've
written books on technical topics and
now you're doing this quote boring
management stuff don't you miss some of
the of the geeky stuff no III don't miss
it because well I don't know why but I I
kind of became fed up with technology by
some means I mean seeing technology just
reinventing the wheel somehow in in
certain areas well there's my favorite
topics are like web-services anybody who
has been deeply involved in middleware
and how its structured and we actually
wrote the world a book on it
seeing that web services becomes a high
band reinvents many of the concepts that
have been around for a long time it's
mindless and technology became very
minor on the daily working basis
I saw always organizational and and
process issues and this not only in my
regular work but also as an architecture
reviewer and so I I felt the urgent
needs to have a more impact to not only
consult from the background but to
actually make the faults and errors
myself so so is that the reason why you
became a manager so you have a big
bigger leverage bigger leverage
it's not the ultimate power that I
strive for but to have a bigger leverage
I mean it might seem as you have more
power it's just you're closer to the
source where things can go wrong really
majorly you're saying is that every
every fish starts thinking at its head I
think that's the same at least I know
food works in English but I don't like
that not saying that every R&D manager
besides me something know how to do the
business but really supporting from that
angle and well I have been consultant to
managers over many years and so I
thought well I in the conversation I
sensed well I think I have something to
say here and I have fun fun working with
people actually I I prepared a list of
things that I thought are crucial if you
want to become an R&D manager let me let
me ask a brand so you say you became a
manager because you kind of thought that
you actually have this additional
leverage it's that true can you give an
example of it's a big change
that you've introduced into an
organization that that where you think
Wow cool that worked that makes that
will be going to that will make a
difference
one example is agility and well for me
it's the way that software should be
developed because agility honors
software as a matter and our classical
waterfall browsers didn't really honor
software and with its complexity and its
behavior and their agility does a much
better job now how do you introduce
agility to an organization as
documentation that is quite traditional
in it's quite additional in its sense
either you have guys around you and
enough grassroots power or you won't
succeed and now for example in my today
is position I can help from a management
level and support and really foresters
such change initiatives changing the
mindset at at all levels and so this is
what I operate today really at any any
level from an individual contributor
developer to a senior management level
and explaining talking changing mindset
okay
so you've started saying that you've
prepared a list before I interrupted you
so let's get back to the list you've
prepared maybe you say again what this
was about it's about what's important in
a manager's life what kind of skill set
and mindset you should have one is for
example the the listening skills to to
really feel and sense the sunset between
sentences whenever you talk to somebody
you appear your superior any any
employee there's also things that are
set between the lines and so this is
kind of necessary to be a good manager I
feel because very often
as a manager you you're the one who gets
informed about stuff the last and so
with this reading between the lines you
have the chance to still get your
information and sense where you might
need to look into more detail so reading
between the lines can for example mean
that you actually so I mean I don't know
how many levels of managers are between
you and the individual developer I don't
know today there's one level I'm on
additional level one additional right so
so so what this means if I understand
you correctly is that sometimes you walk
around in the trenches where the real
guys sit and talk to them and skip the
guy between you two talk to these people
and and to understand their feelings
right exactly and so for preparing for
this show I thought well how could you
as a developer today like train or
exercise those the skill set and I
remembered that some situations where
peers of me is to other developers or
the requirements engineer and the
developer had some conflict and some
conflict resolution and negotiation
conversations with them supporting them
and and resolving my own conflicts when
I had some with others helped me a lot
and and and practicing this kind of
skill set huh so acting as the well the
the the the the the third party that
tries to help the office agree on
something for example yes thank you many
Germans called Schlick no I don't know
the English term okay another thing is
what what helps you create lis in
preparing for any R&D manager position
is leading without Authority or leading
without power and this what I mean what
that is for example the architect an
architect has typically no role power
from power has no line responsibility
there but still he needs to get things
achieved he needs to change things he
needs
have an influence on on decisions
reviews things and either as architect
or even as a developer you have the
chance to to make such impacts and and
be challenged with with such situations
in big initiatives or any projects
special projects that are set up
regularly in your organization so why
don't you put volunteer next time and
try try to lead basically without the
power and try to how that how that works
out because at the end of the day as the
line manager you do the same I was about
to ask that because why would you want
to train leading without power if your
goal is to become a manager who has the
role power because knowledge workers are
in software development you don't lead
with power if you lead with power you
demotivate and that is actually the last
you you like to do ok ok
another thing is be really well
self-managed with that I mean time
management like the Eisenhower rules to
the important and urgent stuff first and
the four categories I don't explain in
detail to use use Wikipedia on that the
Eisenhower shown out right yeah and this
is so I mean this resolves your own
stress level and actually makes you then
able to lead also others if you are
overburdened with your daily work anyway
it might not be a good starting
situation leading others I mean you know
we aren't paid by those guys but I think
it's still worthwhile hinting at the
manager tools podcast where they talk
about the essentials of management and I
think one of them is delegation so you
have to be able to let loose and let
somebody else do something and the other
one I think is coaching one and once and
you know these kinds of things so you
should if you're interested in that
stuff go to listening go listen to the
manager tools podcast I started off with
the listening skills but equally
important are the communication skills
there's one saying in one bow
my first to understand then to be
understood I think believe it's part of
the seven Habits of Highly Effective
People around us and that's very true in
the daily life so whenever you had then
understood what's going on to
communicate in a proper way becomes
essential so being able to talk with a
certain sensibility of who you talk with
and tune yourself basically to the your
counterpart as it also involve you
certainly have heard about the disk
model where different people have
different characteristics and some
people like you for example I know that
if I if I if I meet you somewhere and I
now hey Michael great to see you how are
you how are you doing today
your eyes will probably will be okay
because you're not the kind of guy who
has you know loves the small talk stuff
I don't either
so get to the point exactly right so so
also trying to use a communication style
that fits your opposite right so that
one of the things you're saying I mean
that is the disk model or MBTI or any
other model yes thinking in those terms
but just sensing into the other person
what kind of situation is he in when you
well read between the lines well he's
not so happy today he's he had some
trouble whatever then you don't make
jokes about this and I yeah or when you
feel well he's he's overburdened with
something anyway don't give him an
assignment in the first sentence or
things like that right you talked about
communication skills does this also
involve writing or I mean the point I'm
trying to get it is you've written two
books right if do you think that helped
or helps you now so you were able to
communicate complex things technical or
organizational in written form to other
people well it helps me writing emails
fast because of the typing what I meant
yes I noticed I was choking yeah so
being precise in emails and getting
things to the point orally it helps me
as well yes because I mean especially
the pattern spokes help you structure
things sometimes you get so structures
you get so to the point with no
introduction that it also can be a lots
of beneficial but most of the time a I
think it helps you structure your
thoughts focus on what's really the
problem
and differentiate a problem from the
solution yes and not mix them up in any
conversation I I make that I find myself
in this role more and more that I hear
people developers and then you know
domain like what ever talked about
things and they seem to not understand
each other so in my role then is to
listen to what they're saying try to
understand it formulate it very clearly
you know put up a a straw man and say is
that what you're saying and then they
can either agree or not and I think it's
really a consequence of of writing a lot
and as you say of this all this pattern
stuff
yeah the structured thinking about stuff
and well I mean this is what I learned
this is the connection between my past
career and my today's career if you
think about organizational development
if you think about roles about processes
about interactions suddenly you're again
in the pattern space I mean setting up
an organization lining out the
organization how it's supposed to work
how individuals might fill a certain
role and what kind of things might go
wrong in that role that's very very
similar at the end of the day to to how
we talk about patterns I mean why are
their organizational patterns out there
why is that a big field in our pattern
communicate because it's exactly it's
very similar to software design at the
end of and even if you look at CRC cards
right they are about our eyes a little
bit there about entities their
responsibilities and the interactions
and I mean that's exactly what the team
structure and an organizational
structure is yeah and so this is this is
part of a job description as an manager
to
care about that and whenever you have a
new role a new position filled with
somebody this person will bring with him
his own personality and his own way of
living that responsibility filling out
this role and there your your demanded
as an manager to look does this work out
is there any lack of training is there
something needed or do you need to shape
your other roles in positions
differently to share the workload better
and more efficient more things on your
list more things on my list well it
helps if you have been in the roles that
you lead actually so for example you
become a team lead or a software
development team it helps when you have
been developer as we discussed before if
you have looked into testing if you have
a project manager within your team when
you do more classical software
development it helps when you have been
a project manager to understand what the
the daily life and the the trouble could
be in those position you're saying you
it's good if you have been in the roles
of the people you now manage yes
okay very generally yeah it just helps
you being better understanding to your
people
so this somehow opposes the idea that
you that there is something such as
general management so like it doesn't
matter whether you manage a bunch of
software developers or a bunch of coffee
salesmen I tend to think the same thing
but there are other folks and for
example I think the manager tools guys
advocate that who say it doesn't matter
it really management is always the same
I think uh how do I put that politically
correct at a close level to software
developers at the first two levels or so
you should be really well understanding
what is going on
have a proper domain understanding have
a understanding about what you work with
because you have to support the
environment and cannot solely rely on
that somebody will tell you the right
things
have you ever owned gut feeling about it
the higher you get up I I tend to agree
that general management is an important
can be a very big factor and you need
less domain expertise because ultimately
I mean how old do we get and how many
domains can we really gain deep inside
is one thing and the pattern repeats
itself at a higher level you have two
experts you lead managers that lead
themselves again with a hundred or
thousand guys and I guess even if you
say that on a lower level you do need
domain know-how and expertise in the
fields of those people you lead you
probably agree that maybe 60 or 70
percent are generic management practices
and then only these 40 or 30% is the the
specific knowledge right all I said
about communication skills is yourself
well and focus for next thing I like to
introduce its focus on results is that
is general management and this this is
just very very common and it's just the
domain expertise and and really the
understanding of for example software
development that is the extra 30 40 %
maybe if you want to first put it into
percentages yeah so focus on results is
something was that important well it's I
I give a counter example whenever there
is a new assignment whenever there is a
decision pending think really on who who
has to benefit first should I introduce
this technology this concept because I
like it so much because they're so cool
because I want to learn about it or
because my project at hand has the
lowest or a
experiences the lowest risk and the
company and approach egg the biggest
benefit of it I mean focus really on
your decisions on the on the end result
and do proper risk mitigation and put
yourself out of the line of decisions
your personal tendencies so to to quote
a pattern that we've review today that
you have written at least co-written
objectify decision-making right right
not don't do it because you like it but
really provide a clear rationale and
reasons and trade-offs for decisions you
make right it also helps you say if
you're as in something in case something
goes wrong
exactly I mean this is focus on on the
project results on the on the health of
the organization first before you think
too much about yourself and I mean that
is what I see we humans get into our
ways too easily in in decisions or in
our daily work so how do you succeed as
a manager what do you have to do to to
well in the end you want to be promoted
not you personally but as a manager you
want to make career you want to be
promoted so what is it
what are you judged by when are you
considered successful as a manager and
hence are promoted when my people are
happy when my results are okay to create
when there's trust from my superiors
that I could manage even greater
challenges right so in this trust is the
gut feeling that is the warm fuzzy
feeling you leave with others you leave
with your organization that this
organization trusts you I mean this is
trusting you this promotion and that and
that is that is what I wanted to get it
and thank you that you said these things
because this kind of realises that you
don't you're not you're not incentivized
for putting bringing in to level stuff
but you are going to be remoted if your
guys do good work so that's why what you
said before actually make sort of sense
and - well I
and what kind of advice would I give you
whether you should consider it I mean
it's really the question ask yourself
why you would like to be a manager it's
what for what is what would be your
motivation and there are some healthy
motivations that will get you really
advanced and there are some motivations
that that get you stuck then at at
latest at the next level or so and some
healthy motivations is well have a have
a bigger impact feel comfortable with
working enjoying working with people
caring about them being being a servant
for the organization for for the bigger
success all of this sounds great bright
and shiny there have to be some
disadvantages so what is bad about being
a manager what's the most difficult
thing you have to do what is unpleasant
about all that I mean the most
unpleasant thing which is which could
happen to a developer or an employee is
exactly the most unpleasant thing for a
manager and this is when you in a
downturn as we we experience right now
worldwide you would have to let go
people
I mean having having those conversations
explaining explaining why your
organization fails to withstand the
downturn why there is no position
anymore
someone's the most difficult but now
making it not so traumatic as really
letting somebody go giving giving
feedback and critical situations or well
when some when you think well this
person should know what his behavior
does to others or the organization
basically some how should I say that
corrective feedback and those are always
then interesting challenging discuss
discussions but it's really where you
can employ your full
set yeah yeah so so well yeah it's what
I would have expected being the the the
messenger for bad news right even if the
small bad news or big bad news so the
you you don't feel frustrated that you
are in this big environment where there
is a lot of inflexible structure around
you and you maybe don't have as much
impact as you would like to have isn't
that another of these another one of
these potentially unpleasant things
well you mentioned with the reason that
I or the situation that I work in big
organization yes well big organizations
and that is not only my company I think
that is a general pattern I know that
it's a general pattern actually talking
through to colleagues and having been in
multiple big corporations big
corporations our complex yes big
corporations have challenges and in
communication or Irish the coordination
well for me it's it's the complexity
what excited me early in my career in
technology it's the complexity in
organization to deal with and still be
efficient still be successful what what
excites me in my my daily life uh-huh
okay so I guess we're at the end of what
we had prepared is there anything else
you want to say that I forgot to ask no
I think we're we're through with what we
blend for for that what I like to
mention please give us feedback on our
webpage or write me a personal email if
you feel it's too personal I am very
happy about feedback and if you have any
recommendations okay so I guess then
that's it for today and I guess maybe
perhaps in half a year or something we
do the reverse thing where I talk about
being a consultant and you ask me about
it I'm looking forward to there okay
thanks for listening bye thanks bye
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineering
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at SE - rally or net if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for su radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and thus left of button to contact
the team please send email to team at se
- radio net or if you're specific to an
episode please use the comments facility
on the website so other people can react
to your comments this episode of se
radio as well as all other episodes are
licensed under the creative comments 2.5
license please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the pot size Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas on top